NICOLÁS URDANETA

n.urdaneta@duke.edu nicolasurdaneta.github.io (+1) 217-9795876

Last updated: September 2024

Profile

I am an economics PhD student at Duke University. My current research interests are in trade, firm dynamics, and macroeconomic development. I also have some ongoing projects on internal migration and displacement in Colombia and gender bias in student evaluations of teaching.

EDUCATION

Ph.D. Economics, Duke Univeristy .	2022 - Present
M.A. Economics, Universidad de los Andes - Colombia (cum laude).	2019 - 2021
B.A. Economics, Universidad de los Andes - Colombia (cum laude).	2015 - 2019

Published Papers

The Size and Life-Cycle Growth of Plants: The Role of Productivity, Demand, and Wedges. (2024). The Review of Economic Studies. With Marcela Eslava and John Haltiwanger. Document available here.

Businesses and Inequality in Latin America. (Accepted). Oxford Open Economicis. With Marcela Eslava, Marcela Meléndez, Gabriel Ulysea, and Ignacio Flores. LACIR working paper version here.

WORKING PAPERS

Business Size, Development, and Inequality in Latin America: A Tale of One Tail. (2023). Policy Research Working Paper 10584. © World Bank, Washington, DC. With *Marcela Eslava*, *Marcela Meléndez*, and *Laura Tenjo*. Working paper available here.

Market Concentration, Market Fragmentation, and Inequality in Latin America. (2021). UNDP LAC Working Paper No. 11. Background Paper for the UNDP LAC Regional Human Development Report 2021. With *Marcela Eslava* and *Marcela Meléndez*. Working paper available here.

"Talented" Men and "Kind" Women? Gender Bias in Student Evaluations of Teaching. (2021). Documento CEDE No. 46. (Master's thesis). Document available here. In the media: El Espectador.

Work in Progress

Equilibrium Gender Discrimination in Student Evaluations of Teaching. With Sara Ayllon, Lars Lefgren, Richard Patterson, and Olga Stoddard.

Reconciling the Effects of Migration: Do the Opportunity Costs Shape the Local Effects?. With Mateo Arbeláez and Juan Sebastián Muñoz.

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Research Assistant for Daniel Xu and Felix Tintelnot, Duke University. (Aug. 2024 - Present).

Research Assistant for Marcela Eslava, Universidad de Los Andes. Main research projects joint with John Haltiwanger and Marcela Meléndez (Jun. 2019 - Jul. 2022).

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

TEACHER ASSISTANT - DUKE UNIVERSITY

First-year Ph.D. Econometrics (profs. Matt Masten, Adam Rosen, and Anna Bykhovskaya) 2023 Fall - 2024 Spring

Teacher Assistant - Universidad de Los Andes

Impact Evaluation for Public Policy (prof. Adriana Camacho) 2020 II
Intermediate Econometrics (prof. Mateo Arbeláez) 2020 Summer
World Economic History (prof. Leopoldo Fergusson and Juan Sebastián Galán) 2020 I
Intermediate Macroeconomics (prof. David Pérez and Andrés Zambrano) 2019 II & 2020 I

Referee Services

Economía LACEA Journal.

LANGUAGES

English	Fluent	Spanish	Native Language
REFERENCES			
Marcela Eslava	Full Professor and meslava@uniandes.edu.	Economics Dean,	Universidad de Los Andes.
John Haltiwanger	Distinguished Universit	y Professor, University	of Maryland. halt@umd.edu
Adriana Camacho	Associate Professor, Un	iversidad de Los Ande	s. adcamach@uniandes.edu.co
Lars Lefgren	Department Chair	and Professor,	Bringham Young University.